
================================================================================
PAGE 0
================================================================================
Auto-Regressive Moving Diffusion Models for Time Series Forecasting
Jiaxin Gao12*, Qinglong Cao12*, Yuntian Chen2鈥?
1Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai, China
2Ningbo Institute of Digital Twin, Eastern Institute of Technology, Ningbo, Zhejiang, China
jiaxingao@sjtu.edu.cn; caoql2022@sjtu.edu.cn; ychen@eitech.edu.cn
Abstract
Time series forecasting (TSF) is essential in various domains,
and recent advancements in diffusion-based TSF models have
shown considerable promise. However, these models typi-
cally adopt traditional diffusion patterns, treating TSF as a
noise-based conditional generation task. This approach ne-
glects the inherent continuous sequential nature of time se-
ries, leading to a fundamental misalignment between diffu-
sion mechanisms and the TSF objective, thereby severely
impairing performance. To bridge this misalignment, and
inspired by the classic Auto-Regressive Moving Average
(ARMA) theory, which views time series as continuous se-
quential progressions evolving from previous data points, we
propose a novel Auto-Regressive Moving Diffusion (ARMD)
model to first achieve the continuous sequential diffusion-
based TSF. Unlike previous methods that start from white
Gaussian noise, our model employs chain-based diffusion
with priors, accurately modeling the evolution of time se-
ries and leveraging intermediate state information to improve
forecasting accuracy and stability. Specifically, our approach
reinterprets the diffusion process by considering future series
as the initial state and historical series as the final state, with
intermediate series generated using a sliding-based technique
during the forward process. This design aligns the diffusion
model鈥檚 sampling procedure with the forecasting objective,
resulting in an unconditional, continuous sequential diffu-
sion TSF model. Extensive experiments conducted on seven
widely used datasets demonstrate that our model achieves
state-of-the-art performance, significantly outperforming ex-
isting diffusion-based TSF models.
Code 鈥?https://github.com/daxin007/ARMD
Introduction
Time series forecasting (TSF) plays a pivotal role in vari-
ous real-world applications, including transportation plan-
ning (Fang et al. 2022), energy management (Gao et al.
2023a, 2024), and financial market analysis (Lopez-Lira and
Tang 2023). With the development of deep-learning technol-
ogy, numerous advanced deep-learning TSF models (Piao
et al. 2024; Wu et al. 2023; Zhou et al. 2021) have been
*These authors contributed equally.
鈥燙orresponding author
Copyright 漏 2025, Association for the Advancement of Artificial
Intelligence (www.aaai.org). All rights reserved.
Figure 1: The comparison between (a) existing diffusion-
based time series forecasting methods and (b) our methods.
proposed. Notably, diffusion-based models have emerged as
some of the most promising methods in the realm of TSF
tasks (Meijer and Chen 2024; Yang et al. 2024).
Diffusion models have garnered significant attention in
computer vision due to their capability to generate high-
quality images (Ho, Jain, and Abbeel 2020; Rombach et al.
2022; Cao et al. 2024). These methods typically consist of
two main phases: the forward diffusion process, where noise
is progressively added to an image until it transforms into
white Gaussian noise, and the reverse denoising process,
where a denoising network gradually removes noise to re-
construct the original image. While diffusion models are
predominantly used in computer vision, recent research has
begun exploring their applications in the TSF task.
Current diffusion-based TSF methods (Tashiro et al.
2021; Alcaraz and Strodthoff 2022; Yuan and Qiao 2024)
The Thirty-Ninth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-25)
16727

================================================================================
PAGE 1
================================================================================
typically follow traditional diffusion patterns, treating TSF
as a noise-based conditional generation task. As illustrated
in Fig. 1 (a), the forward diffusion process gradually adds
noise to transform the original time series into white Gaus-
sian noise. During forecasting, the historical series serves
as a condition, and the reverse denoising process converts
the white Gaussian noise into the predicted future time se-
ries. While these noise-based conditional diffusion methods
have shown some success, they often overlook the continu-
ous sequential nature of time series, leading to a misalign-
ment between the diffusion mechanism and the TSF objec-
tive, which significantly suppresses performance. Addition-
ally, by directly diffusing the true series into white Gaussian
noise, these methods fail to capture and utilize the valuable
intermediate information within the evolution of time series.
To address these limitations, we propose a new con-
tinuous sequential diffusion-based model, Auto-Regressive
Moving Diffusion (ARMD), for TSF. Drawing inspira-
tion from the principles of the classic TSF theory, Auto-
Regressive Moving Average (ARMA), the time series can
be viewed as a continuous progression of data points, where
each new point is influenced by past data points and includes
some random noise. This relationship can be expressed as:
xt = 蠒1xt鈭? + 蠒2xt鈭? + 路 路 路 + 蠒pxt鈭抪
+ 胃1系t鈭? + 胃2系t鈭? + 路 路 路 + 胃q系t鈭抭 + 系t,
where xt represents the value at time step t, and 系t represents
the random noise. Our model fully leverages the inherent
features of time series, which exhibit continuous sequential
evolution and form a chain of dependencies characterized
by prior information. Unlike previous diffusion methods that
focus solely on denoising, ARMD is designed to simulate
and learn the underlying evolution of the series.
As illustrated in Fig. 1 (b), our proposed ARMD intro-
duces a novel approach where the future series is progres-
sively diffused into the historical series during the forward
diffusion/evolution process. In contrast, the reverse denois-
ing/devolution process leverages the historical series to fore-
cast the future series. This approach conceptualizes the evo-
lution of a time series as a diffusion process, where each
intermediate series at a given time step represents a specific
state within this process. Consequently, the forward diffu-
sion process can also be described as a forward evolution
process of the time series, and the traditional reverse denois-
ing process is reinterpreted as a reverse devolution process.
Unlike conventional methods that introduce noise to gen-
erate intermediate states from the original series, ARMD
derives intermediate states by sliding the series according
to the diffusion steps. This results in a deterministic pro-
cess that eliminates the uncertainty typically associated with
noise. These deterministic intermediate series are then em-
ployed for model training. In the reverse devolution pro-
cess, a linear-based devolution (denoising) network is uti-
lized to devolve the series through a distance-based method.
Specifically, the devolution network, equipped with a lin-
ear module, estimates the distance between an intermediate
state (series) and the target series. It then adaptively adjusts
the weighting of the intermediate state and the estimated dis-
tance based on the time step, ultimately generating the pre-
diction for the target series and its evolution trend.
During the final sampling/forecasting phase, the model
begins with the historical time series and gradually trans-
forms it into the future time series. This approach aligns the
sampling process with the ultimate prediction objective, re-
moving the need for conditional generation. Consequently,
our method improves stability during both training and sam-
pling, resulting in enhanced forecasting performance.
鈥?Inspired by classical time series theory, specifically
ARMA, and viewing the evolution of time series as an
entire diffusion process, we propose the Auto-Regressive
Moving Diffusion (ARMD) model as the first continuous
sequential diffusion-based TSF model.
鈥?By employing a simple sliding operation, our method
leverages the valuable intermediate information of the
time series as intermediate states within the diffusion
process. This approach successfully aligns the diffusion
mechanism with the true evolution of time series, natu-
rally leading to improved performance.
鈥?The proposed ARMD is extensively evaluated on the
common TSF benchmarks, and the experimental results
demonstrate that our method achieves state-of-the-art
forecasting performance.
Related Work
Traditional TSF models like ARMA and ARIMA (Box et al.
2015) rely on statistical methods that assume linear relation-
ships between past and present observations to identify pat-
terns. Recently, deep-learning models have gained promi-
nence in TSF. Temporal Convolution Networks (TCNs)
(Wu et al. 2023; Gao et al. 2023b) use convolution layers
to learn temporal dependencies. Transformer-based mod-
els (Xu et al. 2024) are also widely used in TSF. Notably,
PatchTST (Nie et al. 2022) segments the time series into
multiple tokens and uses attention to learn relationships be-
tween them. Client (Gao, Hu, and Chen 2023) and iTrans-
former (Liu et al. 2024) apply the attention mechanism on
the inverted dimensions to capture multivariate correlations.
Additionally, DLinear (Zeng et al. 2023) demonstrates the
efficacy of linear models in TSF tasks.
In the realm of diffusion-based TSF models, TimeGrad
(Rasul et al. 2021) generates future values autoregressively,
suitable for short-term forecasting but suffers from error ac-
cumulation and slow inference for long-term forecasting.
CSDI (Tashiro et al. 2021) avoids autoregressive inference
by incorporating a self-supervised strategy with input mask-
ing. SSSD (Alcaraz and Strodthoff 2022) improves on CSDI
by using a structured state space model instead of Trans-
formers to address quadratic complexity issues, though both
CSDI and SSSD face boundary disharmony problems (Lug-
mayr et al. 2022). TimeDiff (Shen and Kwok 2023) miti-
gates these limitations with inductive biases tailored for time
series data. D3VAE (Li et al. 2022) uses a coupled diffusion
probabilistic model for data augmentation, integrating multi-
scale denoising score matching and disentangling multivari-
ate latent variables for enhanced accuracy and stability. TS-
Diff (Kollovieh et al. 2024) employs a self-guidance mecha-
nism during inference without changing the training process,
16728

================================================================================
PAGE 2
================================================================================
excelling in forecasting and synthetic data generation. mr-
Diff (Shen, Chen, and Kwok 2024) applies seasonal-trend
decomposition for trend extraction and non-autoregressive
denoising. Similarly, MG-TSD (Fan et al. 2024) leverages
data granularity levels as intermediate diffusion targets for
better forecasting. Diffusion-TS (Yuan and Qiao 2024) intro-
duces an encoder-decoder Transformer framework with dis-
entangled temporal representations to generate high-quality
multivariate time series samples from noisy inputs.
Preliminary
Time Series Forecasting. Given a historical time series
X鈭扡+1:0, where L denotes the series length. The objective
of TSF is to forecast the future values of the same series, de-
noted as X1:T , where T represents the number of time steps
to forecast. X鈭扡+1:T can be either a univariate time series
or a multivariate time series.
Diffusion Models. The traditional diffusion models first
progressively add noise (Ho, Jain, and Abbeel 2020) to the
original data X0 through a forward diffusion process, pro-
ducing noised data XT . Then the diffusion process is re-
versed to reconstruct the original data or generate the new
data. The intermediate state in each step of diffusion can
be calculated based on the original data X0 and the ran-
dom noise applied at each step. Trained to predict the added
noise or the intermediate state at each step, diffusion mod-
els generate new instances by iterative sampling from white
Gaussian noise. Diffusion models have been widely applied
in diverse fields and have demonstrated notable advantages
in generation quality (Croitoru et al. 2023).
Diffusion Models for TSF in ARMD. In our proposed
ARMD, TSF is aligned with diffusion models by associ-
ating the time series with states in the diffusion process.
The future series X1:T would serve as the initial state of
the diffusion process. Following the notation convention in
(Shen and Kwok 2023), the initial state is further indicated
as X0
1:T . Conversely, the historical time series X鈭扡+1:0 is
the final state of the diffusion process, which is further de-
noted as XT
鈭扡+1:0. Here, the upper index of X indicates its
state in the diffusion process, while the lower index repre-
sents the time steps it encompasses. In ARMD, the length of
the historical series matches that of the future series, allow-
ing the historical series to be defined as XT
鈭扵 +1:0. The inter-
mediate state corresponds to a series transitioning from the
future series to the historical series, denoted as Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰.
Proposed Model
In this section, we introduce Auto-Regressive Moving Dif-
fusion (ARMD), a novel continuous sequential diffusion-
based TSF model. ARMD鈥檚 overview is depicted in Fig. 2.
Forward Diffusion (Evolution) of ARMD
In ARMD, the evolution of a time series is conceptualized
as a diffusion process. Here, the future series X0
1:T serves
as the initial state of the forward diffusion (evolution) pro-
cess. In contrast, the historical series XT
鈭扵 +1:0 represents the
final state, as opposed to white Gaussian noise commonly
used in traditional diffusion models. Unlike conventional ap-
proaches that progressively add noise, the intermediate state
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 in ARMD corresponds to sliding the X0
1:T by t
steps, approaching the historical series XT
鈭扵 +1:0. This ap-
proach leverages the properties of time series, where each in-
termediate state in the diffusion process reflects an interme-
diate series in the time series evolution. The process where
Xt鈭?
2鈭抰:T 鈭抰+1 is diffused to Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 represents a single-step
movement towards the historical series, as illustrated in Fig.
2, akin to the q process in denoising diffusion probabilistic
model (DDPM) (Ho, Jain, and Abbeel 2020). The process
can be formally expressed as:
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 = Slide(Xt鈭?
2鈭抰:T 鈭抰+1, 1),
where Slide(X, k) denotes the k-step movement of the se-
ries window X towards the historical series. Furthermore,
at any time step t, Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 can be directly obtained us-
ing X0
1:T , similar to the process in DDPM. Building upon
DDPM鈥檚 foundational assumption, we extend this principle
to our sliding sampling process. This extension enables us
to calculate the evolution trends and train the devolution net-
work effectively. Specifically, the t-step forward process can
be rewritten as:
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 = Slide(X0
1:T , t) = 鈭毬眛X0
1:T +
1 鈭捖眛zt,
where zt represents the evolution trend from the series X0
to Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰, functionally similar to the noise added in the
original DDPM. Given that each time step of Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 is
deterministic, zt can be calculated as:
zt = (
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 鈭扻0
1:T )/
Here, zt serves as the ground truth for the optimization ob-
jective at each time step. In this diffusion scheme, the max-
imum number of diffusion steps T equals the length of the
series to be predicted.
Reverse Denoising (Devolution) of ARMD
The reverse process in ARMD utilizes the historical series
鈭扵 +1:0 to iteratively generate (forecast) the future series
1:T . At each devolution step, the linear-based devolution
network R(.) predicts the evolution trend zt, which is used
to devolve Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 to Xt鈭?
2鈭抰:T 鈭抰+1. Given an intermediate
state (series) Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 and the diffusion step t, R(.) pre-
dicts 藛
X0(Xt, t, 胃) for the future series X0
1:T . More specif-
ically, within the devolution network R(.), a linear module
first provides a prediction of the distance D from the input
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 to X0
1:T :
D = Linear(Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰).
Then, the diffusion step t is used to adaptively balance the
interaction between the distance prediction D and the input
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰, enabling the network to produce more accurate
predictions. Particularly, as t decreases, the input Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰
16729

================================================================================
PAGE 3
================================================================================
Figure 2: Illustration of the diffusion process in ARMD. During the forward diffusion process, the future series is progressively
diffused into the historical series. Conversely, the reverse denoising process utilizes the historical series to iteratively generate/-
forecast the future series. For clarity, the series X is only annotated with an upper index to indicate its state.
becomes closer to the target X0
1:T , so the model鈥檚 output
should increasingly resemble the input, placing less empha-
sis on D. Conversely, as t increases, the model places greater
reliance on D. This adaptive balancing can be mathemati-
cally expressed as:
X0(Xt, t, 胃) = W(t) 鈭梄t
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 + (1 鈭抌W(t)) 鈭桪
(1 + cW(t))d
where W(t) represents a weight coefficient that decreases
as t increases, ranging from 0 to 1. We initialize W(t) with
the predefined coefficients 炉伪t of DDPM, and it is updated
along with the linear module鈥檚 parameters during training.
The hyper-parameters b, c, and d are leveraged to balance
the interaction between the distance prediction D and the
input Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰. To increase sample diversity and prevent
over-fitting, a small deviation is added to the input of R(.)
during the training process.
After obtaining the prediction 藛
X0(Xt, t, 胃), the predicted
evolution trend 藛z(t, 胃) can be calculated as:
藛z(t, 胃) = (
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 鈭捤?
X0(Xt, t, 胃))/
鈭?. (6)
With the ground truth zt calculated in Equation (3) and
the prediction 藛z(t, 胃), the training objective is formulated as:
L胃 = Et[|zt 鈭捤唞(t, 胃)|].
Sampling/Forecasting of ARMD
In the sampling phase, starting from the historical series
鈭扵 +1:0, ARMD iteratively generates the future series
1:T , which successfully aligns the sampling process with
the TSF objective, making the model an unconditional diffu-
sion TSF model. The method follows the sampling approach
from DDIM (Song, Meng, and Ermon 2020), replacing the
predicted noise 系胃(xt, t) with the predicted evolution trend
藛z(t, 胃). The sampling process from t to t 鈭? (akin to the p
process in DDPM/DDIM) can be expressed as:
Xt鈭?
2鈭抰:T 鈭抰+1 =鈭毬眛鈭?
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 鈭掆垰1 鈭捖眛藛z(t, 胃)
鈭毬眛
1 鈭捖眛鈭? 鈭捪?
t 藛z(t, 胃) + 蟽t系t,
where 藛z(t, 胃) is the predicted evolution trend at the time
step t, and 系t 鈭糔(0, I). Since the series evolution in
ARMD is deterministic, we remove the noise term 蟽t系t. The
content within the parentheses in the first term is actually
X0(Xt, t, 胃). Thus, the simplified equation is:
Xt鈭?
2鈭抰:T 鈭抰+1 = 鈭毬眛鈭? 藛
X0(Xt, t, 胃)
1 鈭捖眛鈭? 鈭捪?
t 藛z(t, 胃).
To accelerate sampling, k steps can be skipped at each
iteration, and the process can be further inferred as:
Xt鈭択
1鈭抰+k:T 鈭抰+k = 鈭毬眛鈭択 藛
X0(Xt, t, 胃)
1 鈭捖眛鈭択 鈭捪?
t 藛z(t, 胃).
(10)
For better understanding, the training and sampling pro-
cedures are detailed in Algorithm 1 and Algorithm 2.
16730

================================================================================
PAGE 4
================================================================================
Algorithm 1: Training.
Require: Maximum number of diffusion steps T, which
also represents the length of the historical/future series;
Predefined coefficients 炉伪0:T .
1: repeat
Sample X0
1:T from the training set;
Sample t 鈭糢niform({1, 2, . . . , T});
Generate the diffused sample Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 using Equa-
tion (2), and calculate the evolution trend zt using
Equation (3);
Use the devolution network R(.) to generate the pre-
dicted sample 藛
X0(Xt, t, 胃) using Equation (5), and
obtain the predicted evolution trend 藛z(t, 胃) using
Equation (6);
Calculate the loss L胃 using Equation (7);
Update the devolution network R(.) of ARMD by
taking a gradient descent step on 鈭囄窵;
8: until converged.
Algorithm 2: Sampling/Forecasting.
Require: Historical series XT
鈭扵 +1:0; Trained devolution
network R(.); Sampling interval 鈭唗; Predefined coef-
ficients 炉伪0:T .
1: for t = T to 0 by 鈭唗 do
Obtain 藛
X0(Xt, t, 胃) using Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 and t with the
devolution network R(.), and calculate the corre-
sponding evolution trend 藛z(t, 胃) using Equation (6);
Update Xt
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 using Equation (10);
4: end for
5: Output the prediction of X0
1:T .
Experiments
Experimental Settings
ARMD is evaluated on seven widely used benchmark
datasets, including Solar Energy (Lai et al. 2018), Exchange
(Lai et al. 2018), Stock (Yoon, Jarrett, and Van der Schaar
2019), and four ETT datasets (Zhou et al. 2021). We com-
pare ARMD with five advanced diffusion-based TSF mod-
els: Diffusion-TS (Yuan and Qiao 2024), MG-TSD (Fan
et al. 2024), TSDiff (Kollovieh et al. 2024), D3VAE (Li
et al. 2022), TimeGrad (Rasul et al. 2021). Additionally,
some other advanced TSF models, including iTransformer
(Liu et al. 2024), TimesNet (Wu et al. 2023), DLinear (Zeng
et al. 2023), PatchTST (Nie et al. 2022), and Client (Gao,
Hu, and Chen 2023) are also compared with ARMD.
For all datasets, the historical length and prediction length
are both set to 96. Following the evaluation methodology
employed in a previous study (Zhou et al. 2021), we calcu-
late the mean squared error (MSE) and mean absolute error
(MAE) on z-score normalized data, enabling a consistent as-
sessment of various variables.
Comparison with Diffusion-Based Models
The multivariate forecasting results, comparing our pro-
posed ARMD with various advanced diffusion-based TSF
models, are summarized in Table 1, with each model鈥檚
results averaged over 10 sampling runs. Notably, ARMD
demonstrates superior forecasting performance, achieving
optimal results in 12 out of the 14 experimental settings.
Our extensive experiments reveal that while other diffusion-
based TSF models can achieve effective results on specific
datasets, they often suffer from instability, performing well
in certain scenarios but deviating significantly from the true
values in others, which indicates a lack of generalization
across diverse data. In contrast, ARMD consistently exhibits
robust performance across all datasets, suggesting a higher
degree of reliability and adaptability to various multivariate
forecasting challenges. Specifically, on the ETTm1 dataset,
ARMD achieves a substantial 47.7% reduction in MSE and
a 30.1% reduction in MAE compared to the second-best
model, D3VAE. On the Stock dataset, ARMD surpasses TS-
Diff, the second-best model in this setting, with a 28.8% re-
duction in MSE and a 26.3% reduction in MAE. Further-
more, ARMD attains more than a 10% reduction in both
MSE and MAE on the Solar Energy, ETTh1, and Exchange
datasets compared to the nearest competitor. These results
indicate that ARMD is the best diffusion-based TSF model.
Comparison with Other TSF Models
As demonstrated in Table 2, ARMD consistently outper-
forms other advanced models in multivariate TSF tasks.
The comparative results for other TSF models are primar-
ily sourced from iTransformer (Liu et al. 2024), with the
Stock dataset being an exception, where additional evalua-
tions are conducted using official implementations to ensure
a thorough analysis. ARMD achieves the highest number of
best counts, indicating its consistent ability to surpass other
TSF methods across multiple benchmarks. These results not
only establish ARMD as the leading diffusion-based TSF
model but also underscore its superiority over existing mod-
els. Overall, these findings highlight ARMD鈥檚 promise as a
robust and effective solution for multivariate TSF tasks.
Qualitative Analysis
As illustrated in Fig. 3, we qualitatively analyze the per-
formance of ARMD by comparing it with the advanced
diffusion-based model, Diffusion-TS. Given the same his-
torical series, both models make 10 independent predictions
for the future series. Our analysis reveals that ARMD con-
sistently produces more stable and accurate predictions, par-
ticularly in scenarios involving high peak values. This is
in contrast to Diffusion-TS, which shows greater variability
and less precision in similar settings. We attribute ARMD鈥檚
superior performance to its deterministic training process
and the reduced sampling steps required during inference.
These features of ARMD not only enhance the model鈥檚 abil-
ity to generate predictions that closely align with actual se-
ries but also result in narrower uncertainty distributions.
Efficiency Comparison
We compare the training and inference efficiency of ARMD
with the diffusion-based TSF models Diffusion-TS, MG-
TSD, and TimeGrad on ETTm1, as shown in Table 3. Due to
16731

================================================================================
PAGE 5
================================================================================
Methods
Metric Solar Energy ETTh1 ETTh2 ETTm1 ETTm2 Exchange Stock Best Count
ARMD (Ours)
0.167
0.445
0.311
0.337
0.181
0.093
0.235
0.236
0.459
0.338
0.376
0.255
0.203
0.269
Diffusion-TS (Yuan and Qiao 2024) MSE
0.181
0.643
0.544
0.678
0.497
0.275
0.416
0.252
0.586
0.494
0.613
0.459
0.382
0.533
MG-TSD (Fan et al. 2024)
0.443
1.096
0.295
0.690
0.202
0.396
0.365
0.529
0.765
0.345
0.631
0.278
0.460
0.453
TSDiff (Kollovieh et al. 2024)
0.352
0.614
0.470
0.686
0.242
0.125
0.330
0.432
0.521
0.418
0.603
0.311
0.240
0.365
D3VAE (Li et al. 2022)
0.416
1.123
0.389
0.644
0.394
0.240
0.345
0.492
0.728
0.373
0.538
0.410
0.371
0.390
TimeGrad (Rasul et al. 2021)
0.359
0.884
0.297
0.661
0.182
0.508
0.333
0.449
0.725
0.349
0.639
0.254
0.554
0.376
Table 1: Result comparisons of multivariate series forecasting with diffusion-based TSF models. The best results are highlighted
in bold. The 鈥淏est Count鈥?column indicates the times of achieving the best result.
Methods
Metric Solar Energy ETTh1 ETTh2 ETTm1 ETTm2 Exchange Stock Best Count
ARMD (Ours)
0.167
0.445
0.311
0.337
0.181
0.093
0.235
0.236
0.459
0.338
0.376
0.255
0.203
0.269
iTransformer (Liu et al. 2024)
0.203
0.386
0.297
0.334
0.180
0.086
0.342
0.237
0.405
0.349
0.368
0.264
0.206
0.413
TimesNet (Wu et al. 2023)
0.250
0.384
0.340
0.338
0.187
0.107
0.427
0.292
0.402
0.347
0.375
0.267
0.234
0.499
DLinear (Zeng et al. 2023)
0.290
0.386
0.333
0.345
0.193
0.088
0.286
0.378
0.400
0.387
0.372
0.292
0.218
0.325
PatchTST (Nie et al. 2022)
0.234
0.414
0.302
0.329
0.175
0.088
0.516
0.286
0.419
0.348
0.367
0.259
0.205
0.524
Client (Gao, Hu, and Chen 2023)
0.199
0.392
0.305
0.336
0.184
0.086
0.352
0.239
0.409
0.353
0.369
0.267
0.206
0.433
Table 2: Result comparisons of multivariate series forecasting with other TSF models. The best results are highlighted in bold.
Training time (s)
Inference time (s)
ARMD (Ours)
11.872
31.650
Diffusion-TS
149.974
1183.593
MG-TSD
834.815
3299.918
TimeGrad
449.792
1749.896
Table 3: Training/inference time (s) of ARMD, Diffusion-
TS, MG-TSD and TimeGrad on the ETTm1 dataset.
the optimized model structure and the reduction in the num-
ber of sampling steps, ARMD achieves more than a tenfold
reduction in both training and inference times compared to
other diffusion models.
Ablation Studies
In this section, we set a range of ablation experiments to
testify diverse components of the proposed ARMD.
Intermediate State Generation Method. ARMD generates
intermediate states using a sliding-based method to maintain
series continuity. An alternative method to generate interme-
diate states involves interpolating between the initial series
1:T and final series XT
鈭扵 +1:0, as described by:
1鈭抰:T 鈭抰 = X0
1:T + (XT
鈭扵 +1:0 鈭扻0
1:T ) 鈭梩/T.
The results of using these interpolation-based intermediate
states are presented in the second row of Table 4. The results
indicate that our sliding-based method consistently outper-
forms the interpolation-based approach across all settings,
underscoring its superiority in preserving series continuity.
16732

================================================================================
PAGE 6
================================================================================
Methods
Metric Solar Energy ETTh1 ETTh2 ETTm1 ETTm2
Exchange Stock Best Count
ARMD (Ours)
0.167
0.445
0.311
0.337
0.181
0.093
0.235
0.236
0.459
0.338
0.376
0.255
0.203
0.269
Interpolation Method
0.184
0.509
0.407
0.359
0.210
0.131
0.249
0.250
0.481
0.373
0.385
0.265
0.249
0.278
T-embedding Method
0.308
0.707
0.376
0.598
0.235
0.233
0.350
0.380
0.589
0.380
0.527
0.331
0.330
0.423
Transformer Backbone
1.343
0.631
0.285
0.578
0.168
0.137
0.239
0.713
0.531
0.341
0.499
0.253
0.242
0.271
Adding Noise
0.199
0.482
0.334
0.552
0.199
0.103
0.328
0.315
0.479
0.353
0.526
0.295
0.228
0.347
Table 4: Ablation experimental results. Interpolation Method: replacing the intermediate state generation method with an
interpolation method. T-embedding Method: using a t-embedding approach for denoising. Transformer Backbone: utilizing
a Transformer-based backbone. Adding Noise: adding sampling noise. The best results are highlighted in bold.
ARMD
Diffusion-TS
Time
Time
value
value
Figure 3: The distributions of 10 different predictions made
by ARMD and Diffusion-TS given the same historical se-
ries. ARMD achieves more stable and accurate predictions.
Devolution/Denosing Learning Method. The devolution
network of ARMD takes a distance-based method to pro-
vide the prediction 藛
X0(Xt, t, 胃) and 藛z(t, 胃), differing from
traditional denoising (devolution) networks that utilize a t-
embedding-based method (Yuan and Qiao 2024; Shen and
Kwok 2023; Shen, Chen, and Kwok 2024). In this method,
the model initially generates a prediction based on the in-
put intermediate state, then embeds the time step t to gen-
erate a t-embedding, and finally combines the t-embedding
with the initial prediction to produce the final output. The re-
sults of applying this t-embedding-based method within the
devolution network are shown in the third row of Table 4,
demonstrating that our distance-based method outperforms
the t-embedding-based method across all settings.
Backbone of the Devolution Network. Many existing
diffusion-based TSF models use a Transformer-based back-
bone in the denoising network (Yuan and Qiao 2024; Li
et al. 2024; Tashiro et al. 2021). Nevertheless, the devolu-
tion network in ARMD uses a linear-based backbone, which
accelerates training and sampling. The impact of replacing
the linear-based backbone with a Transformer-based back-
bone is presented in the fourth row of Table 4. The re-
sults show that the linear-based backbone outperforms the
Transformer-based backbone in most settings (11 out of 14).
Noise in the Sampling Process. Given that the series sam-
pling/forecasting process is deterministic, the noise term
蟽t系t in Equation (8) is set to 0 during sampling/forecasting.
The results of adding sampling noise are shown in the last
row of Table 4, showing that introducing randomness leads
to a decline in model performance.
Conclusion
Inspired by the classic ARMA theory, we creatively intro-
duce an Auto-Regressive Moving Diffusion (ARMD) model
for TSF, which reinterprets the evolution of time series as
a diffusion process. Particularly, regarding the target future
series as the initial state, and the historical series as the fi-
nal state, the intermediate series are generated with the se-
ries slide operations to complete the diffusion process. In
this manner, the sampling procedure of the diffusion model
becomes the series forecasting, which denotes that the dif-
fusion mechanism is successfully aligned with the TSF ob-
jective, and further resulting in an unconditional, continu-
ous sequential diffusion TSF model. The proposed ARMD
is validated across seven widely used datasets, and the ex-
perimental results show that our method effectively suits the
unique characteristics of time series data, and achieves su-
perior forecasting performance.
16733
